hey push students let's cover everything
you need to know for period
6 before we start print out the speed
review sheet to help you follow along
with this video it's free and you can
find the link in the description below
right now look at period 6 circle any
people events vocab things that you
might not quite remember that you know
you need to focus on as we review Once
you're confident that you've mastered a
topic then you can check it off and move
on to the next
one the guilded age was a time of Rapid
economic growth industrialization and
Corruption following the Civil War
American industrialists dominated
American Business by building
corporations becoming some of America's
first millionaires for example Andrew
Carnegie grew his steel business through
a process known as vertical integration
he controlled every stage of the steel
production process from mining to
shipping his finished product John de
Rockefeller grew his Seed Oil Company
through horizontal integration he took
control of the oil refining industry by
buying out his competitors other wealthy
businessmen include Cornel Vanderbilt
who made his fortune in railroads and JP
Morgan who dominated banking these
Robert Barons used trust as a means of
cons validating power controlling
markets and monopolizing Industries they
also used the theory of social Darwinism
or economic survival of the fitness to
justify their fortunes while paying low
wages despite his controversial business
practices Andrew Carnegie was extremely
philanthropic he argued in the gospel of
wealth that the wealthy had a
responsibility to give back for the
betterment of society the industrial
capitalists were able to thrive due to
Les Fair government policies they also
benefited from a long line of pro bus
Republican presidents many of the Robert
Barons contributed financially to
politicians like William McKinley to
maintain their power political
corruption also took place at the state
in local levels often through the use of
political machines who trade in votes
for favors like jobs the most famous of
this time period is William Boss Tweed
who ran tamon call in New York his
Corrupt Practices and exploitation of
immigrants for votes was exposed by the
political cartoons of Thomas Nast
despite widespread political corruption
there was some political reform during
this time the spoil system ended after
the assassination of James Garfield with
the passage of the Pendleton Civil
Service Act and the Sherman anti- Trust
Act was passed in an attempt to limit
the power of monopolies but it was
difficult to enforce to combat low wages
poor working conditions and long hours
workers began to unionize the nights of
Labor founded by Terence powderly was a
Union open to all workers including
skilled unskilled women and
African-Americans but they declined
following the violent Hay Market RI the
American Federation of Labor founded by
Samuel gers is focused on skilled labor
and bread and butter issues like wages
and working conditions strikes were
frequent in the guilded age and usually
occurred because of wage cuts and poor
treatment of workers some of the largest
strikes include the great Railroad
Strike of 1877 the pman strike and the
Homestead Strike they were all put down
sometimes with the help of federal
troops and the strikes of this time were
generally ineffective for bringing about
real change workers as challenges from
industrialization and urbanization Rose
there were calls for reform the social
gospel movement encouraged Christians
especially from the middle class to
address issues such as poverty and
homelessness inspired by the social
gospel movement reformers like Jane
Adams supported the settlement house
movement she and other college educated
women opened the whole house in Chicago
to help provide Child Care Health Care
and education for the poor especially
immigrants and photojournalist Jacob
Bree brought attention to the living
conditions of the urban poor through his
book How the Other Half Lives which led
to legislation in New York for improving
tenament housing Innovations such as
electricity the type operator and the
telephone improve communication and
working conditions these inventions also
increased the number of middle- class
jobs this also led to the development of
street car suburbs as the middle class
sought to escape pollution crime and
other problems associated with
urbanization finally the middle class
had more free time and disposable income
to spend on leisure activities like
attending sporting events going to the
theater and visiting amusement parks and
fairs with the major economic changes
happening in America there were shifts
in Immigration and migration patterns
African-Americans led a mass Exodus out
of the gim Crow South moving West for
economic opportunities and political and
social freedoms also because of
extensive job opportun rapid
urbanization occurred in cities like New
York and Chicago as well as newer
industrial cities like Pittsburgh while
old immigrants like those from Ireland
and Germany continue to seek
opportunities in America new immigrants
from Southern and Eastern Europe also
arrived on America Shores many came
through Ellis Island in New York's
Harbor and eventually settled into
Eastern industrial cities for jobs
immigration also increased from Asia
especially Chinese immigrants who
settled in the west the mass influx of
new immigrants led to AR rise in
nativism which resulted in the Chinese
Exclusion Act following the Civil War
and reconstruction the Southern economy
still revolved around Agriculture and
cash crops some like Henry Grady argued
that South should make an effort to
diversify its economy and embrace
industry greed referred to this as the
new South and some cities like
Birmingham and Memphis adopted new
Industries like steel and lumber despite
promoting economic advancement the South
maintained racism and inequality through
Jim Crow laws this worsened after the
Supreme Court upheld segregation and
plus CV Ferguson but African-Americans
fought back ID the wells L anti- lining
campaigns while Booker T Washington
advocated for economic independence and
vocational education for
African-Americans he also founded the
Tuskegee Institute here 6 also saw the
rapid development of the West between
the 1862 Homestead Act and the
completion of the Transcontinental
Railroad the West Was quickly settled
and developed new Industries like Mining
and cattle ranching were established as
a means to generate wealth in the
western territories while many farmers
moved West for Economic Opportunity The
Mining and ranching industries were
largely dominated by corporations who
had access to vast Capital despite
economic successes the rapidly expanding
population and infrastructure in the
west had devastating negative effects on
the Great Plains Buffalo populations
were decimated and violent conflicts
with natives increased while the NES Pur
fought in the Northwest and the Navajo
in the southwest the Plaines tribes
fought a long and brutal war with the US
Army between the Sand Creek Massacre of
1862 and the Battle of Wounded me in
1890 tribes like the lotu were forced to
abandon their lands or die fighting to
protect it some Americans disapproved of
the violence against natives for example
hel Jackson wrote A Century of Dishonor
to expose the poor treatment of Native
Americans by the American government
many activists began supporting the
process of assimilation one of the most
famous and controversial examples was
the carile school where Native children
were taught English converted to
Christianity and forced to adopt
American cultural values the do
severalty act also supported
assimilation during the guilded Age
Farmers struggled with crop prices High
shipping rates and crippling debt which
often caused farm foreclosures Farmers
tried to combat their struggles and
their exploitation by big businesses by
forming Farmers alliances like the gr
they also formed the populist party
their Omaha platform supported by
metalism the direct election of senators
a graduated income tax and government
ownership of railroad these ideals were
later adopted by the Democratic party
under William Jennings Bran who raided
for president in 1896 upon accepting the
nomination he famously gave the cross of
gold speech supporting the coinage of
silver so what does this look like on
exam day for causation you'll be asked
about the causes of the rise of big
business business or the effects of
Westward expedent for comparison you
could see questions asking you to
compare the guilded age reforms to the
social reforms from period 4 or to
compare the immigrants from the guilded
age to the immigrants who arrived before
the Civil War even for change in
continuity you'll likely be asked about
economic changes like new labor
practices or business structures also
questions could ask about changes in the
new South check out the a plus ultimate
review packet for more help we've got
timeline study guides and Essay practice
follow the link in the description below
for a free preview and if you think this
video is helpful like And subscribe
thanks for watching
[Music]